<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>St. Paul and St. James reconcil'd. A sermon preach'd before the Vniversity of Cambridge, at St. Mary's Church, on Commencement-Sunday in the afternoon, June 30. 1700. ... / By Offspring Blackall, D.D. Chaplain in ordinary to Her Majesty..</title>
            <author>Blackall, Offspring, 1654-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76783</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3050A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC N36965</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">57361813</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 57361813</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177314</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76783)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177314)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2581:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>St. Paul and St. James reconcil'd. A sermon preach'd before the Vniversity of Cambridge, at St. Mary's Church, on Commencement-Sunday in the afternoon, June 30. 1700. ... / By Offspring Blackall, D.D. Chaplain in ordinary to Her Majesty..</title>
                  <author>Blackall, Offspring, 1654-1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The Third Edition..</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by Hen. Hills, in Black-fryars, near the Water-side. For the Benefit of the Poor..</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1700?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.); this item is judged post-1700 by Wing (CD-ROM, 1996).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: badly stained with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  James II, 24 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baccalaureate addresses --  University of Cambridge</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177314:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Reconcil'd.</p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACH'D before the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of</hi> Cambridge, At St. <hi>Mary</hi>'s Church, on <hi>COMMENCEMENT-S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDAY</hi> In the Afternoon, <hi>June</hi> 30. 1700.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>St. JAMES. II. 24.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Ye ſee then how that by Works a Man is juſtify'd and not by Faith only.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Offspring Blackall,</hi> D. D. Chaplain in Ordinary to Her Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Third Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>Hen. Hills,</hi> in <hi>Black-fryars,</hi> near the Water-ſide. For the Benefit of the Poor.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:177314:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>St. JAMES ii. 24.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Ye ſee then how that by Works a Man is juſtify'd, and not by Faith only.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IF it was an uſual thing to take two Texts to a Sermon, I wou'd ſubjoyn to the Words which I have now read to you thoſe in <hi>Rom.</hi> iii. 28. (or ſome other Text out of ſome of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles to the ſame purpoſe. <hi>Therefore we conclude that a Man is juſtify'd by Faith;</hi> and I wou'd read them both together, as the Theme or Subject whereon I intend to diſcourſe at this time.</p>
            <p>For this is indeed my preſent Deſign; not to handle theſe Words of St. <hi>James</hi> by themſelves, that is, as laying down a Notion of Juſtification, to appearance, contrary to what St. <hi>Paul</hi> teaches in that other Text: But to ſhew that St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>James,</hi> tho' they differ in Words and Expreſſions, do yet really both teach the ſame Doctrine; That neither doth St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in excluding <hi>Works</hi> from having any thing to do in our <hi>Justification,</hi> mean to exclude ſuch <hi>Works</hi> as St. <hi>James</hi> here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares to be neceſſary; neither on the other ſide doth St. <hi>James,</hi> in aſſerting the Neceſſity of good <hi>Works,</hi> together with <hi>Faith,</hi> and as the effects of it, mean to attribute more to them than St. <hi>Paul</hi> does.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed to ſhew how theſe two Apoſtles may, as I think, be fairly reconcil'd, it may not be amiſs to premiſe this one thing, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That if that Solution of this Difficulty, which I ſhall by and by propoſe, ſhould not ſeem clear and Satisfactory, and if we cou'd not think of any other way whereby theſe two Divine Writers, might to our Apprehenſion, be reconciled together, and made to ſpeak the ſame thing; it wou'd nevertheleſs in that caſe, be reaſonable to ſtick to the Words of St. <hi>James,</hi> in their ſtrict and moſt natural Signification, and to ſuppoſe that S. <hi>Paul</hi> is to be interpreted by <hi>him,</hi> rather than he by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and conſequently to take for granted, that the Doctrine which we are here taught in expreſs Words by St. <hi>James (viz.</hi> that <hi>Works</hi> are neceſſary as well as <hi>Faith,</hi> to render us ſuch as God will approve of and juſtify at the laſt Day) is undoubtedly true, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' we cou'd not tell which way St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Words might be fairly interpreted in the ſame Senſe. This I ſay appears reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable upon ſeveral Accounts. As namely,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe we have an expreſs Teſtimony of Scripture, that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177314:2"/>
in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Writings <hi>there are ſome things hard to be underſtood which they that are unlearned and unſtable wrest —to their own, Destruction.</hi> [2 <hi>Pet.</hi> iii. 16.] And 'tis probable that thoſe Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces wherein he treats concerning Juſtification by <hi>Faith</hi> only, may be reckon'd in that Number. And this St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſays ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, <hi>viz. That the chief Difficulty of all in St.</hi> Paul<hi>'s Epistles, is his ſo much Commendation of that Faith, which he ſays does justify; by which ignorant Men underſtanding nothing elſe but only an Aſſent of the Mind to the Truths of the Goſpel</hi> which indeed is the prime and moſt proper Notion of the Word) <hi>do thence infer, that a good Life is not neceſſary to juſtify and ſave a Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed if St. <hi>Peter</hi> had not made this Obſervation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Obſcurity of ſome of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Writings, 'tis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs no more than what every one that reads the Bible muſt needs obſerve; <hi>viz.</hi> that the <hi>Epiſtles</hi> of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> eſpecially where he handles Controverſy, are the hardeſt to be underſtood (except perhaps the Propheſies that are not yet accompliſh'd,) of any parts of the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And on the other ſide, it is no leſs obvious to be obſerv'd, that the <hi>Epistle</hi> of St. <hi>James,</hi> and this Chapter of it in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, is, to appearance very plain and clear; and that, both in the Concluſion which it lays down, <hi>viz. that we are juſtify'd by Works, and not by Faith only,</hi> and alſo in the Arguments where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by this Concluſion is made good, from the 14th Verſe of this Chapter to the end.</p>
            <p>Now if the Caſe be thus, as it plainly ſeems to be, nothing can be more unreaſonable than to interpret this Place of St. <hi>James</hi> by thoſe of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that is a plain Place by an obſcure one; and on the other ſide, nothing can be fairer than when we meet with any crabbed or difficult Place in any Autho, to ſee whether his meaning be not elſewhere expreſs'd more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and if it be, to conclude that the intricate Place hath the ſame meaning with the plain one, altho' we know not how well to reconcile the Words and Phraſes thereof to it.</p>
            <p>And this is the Caſe here: For tho' St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>James</hi> were different Writers, yet the Author of both their <hi>Epiſtles</hi> was the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> the Holy Spirit of God, by whoſe Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they both wrote: Their Writings are conſequently both of them Parts of that one everlaſting Goſpel, by which God will judge the World; and they do both of them contain (on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in different Expreſſions) the Articles of the ſame Covenant between God and us. It is reaſonable therefore in this Caſe, to obſerve the ſame Method that we do in other the like Caſes,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177314:3"/>
               <hi>viz.</hi> to put ſuch a Senſe and Interpretation, on any difficult or ambiguous Paſſage that we meet with any where therein, as to make it agree to and conſiſt with thoſe other Paſſages in the ſame Book or Writing, which ſeem to be more plainly expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and of the meaning of which there can be leſs Diſpute.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another Reaſon why I think (if we could not eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile St. <hi>Paul</hi> with St. <hi>James</hi>) we ought rather to embrace the Literal Senſe of St. <hi>James,</hi> than that of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and to conclude with him that good <hi>Works</hi> are neceſſary to our Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Salvation, as well a <hi>Faith</hi> is, becauſe (as is obſerv'd by ſeveral of the Ancients) this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> of St. <hi>James</hi> (as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the firſt of St. <hi>John,</hi> the Second of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and that of St. <hi>Jude</hi>) was written on purpoſe to rectifie the Miſtakes that ſome had fallen into, through their Miſunderſtanding of ſome of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Writings. [v. <hi>Grot.</hi> in <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.21.]</p>
            <p>Now if this be ſo, we may reaſonably conclude, that St. <hi>James</hi> deſigning this Diſcourſe of his concerning <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Works</hi> as a Commentary upon, or an Explication of what St. <hi>Paul</hi> had written before upon the ſame Subject, was very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to avoid all that Obſcurity and Ambiguity of Expreſſion, which had occaſion'd the Writings of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to be ſo groſly miſunderſtood, and wreſted to ſuch ill purpoſes, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves they had been by ſome ignorant and perverſe Men; and conſequently that St. <hi>James</hi> uſes the Words <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Works</hi> in that Senſe, which is moſt natural and obvious, in that Senſe wherein Common Readers were moſt like to underſtand them: Whereas St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Epiſtles</hi> I mean thoſe wherein he handles this ſame Subject) being written with another Deſign, as I ſhall ſhew hereafter, it may well be ſuppoſed that he, having in his writing them an Eye to his main Deſign, (which was to ſhew the Neceſſity of embracing the Chriſtian Faith, and the no Obligation that lay upon <hi>Chriſtians</hi> from the Ceremonial Law of <hi>Moſes</hi>) was more careleſs in his other Expreſſions, as not fearing that any Perſon, inſtructed in the Chriſtian Religion, wou'd ever ſo groſly miſunderſtand and pervert his Words, as to think that he intended to give Encouragement to a lewd and and diſſolute Life.</p>
            <p>But this, nevertheleſs, ſome did think at leaſt they pleaded St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Authority for it, That if Men did but believe aright, it was no great matter how they liv'd. Againſt theſe therefore our Apoſtle St. <hi>James</hi> ſets himſelf in this Chapter, and ſhews at large that Chriſtianity did not conſiſt only in a true and ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox <hi>Faith;</hi> that a bare Belief in Chriſt, or of the Truths of the Goſpel, without bringing forth Fruits in our Life and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:177314:3"/>
anſwerable to ſuch a Belief, would be in no wiſe ſufficient to juſtifie or ſave us.</p>
            <p>And that in writing this, he had an Eye to what St. <hi>Paul</hi> had written before upon the ſame Subject, is farther probable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he makes uſe of that very Inſtance of <hi>Abraham</hi> to prove the Neceſſity of good <hi>Works</hi> together with <hi>Faith,</hi> which St. <hi>Paul</hi> had before brought againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> to ſhew the ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of <hi>Faith</hi> alone without <hi>Works,</hi> that is, without thoſe Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Obſervances, which they would have preſs'd upon all other <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and which they laid more ſtreſs upon, and did put more Confidence in, than in the <hi>weightier Matters of the Law, Juſtice, Mercy and Fidelity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Epiſtle</hi> of St. <hi>James</hi> therefore being written after St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> and ſo, very probably, with a Deſign to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain them where they had been miſunderſtood; it is reaſonable to take for granted, that what St. <hi>James</hi> here plainly aſſerts, touching the neceſſity of good <hi>Works</hi> together with <hi>Faith,</hi> is the Senſe of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> altho' we cou'd not eaſily bring St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Words to it. Eſpecially if it be conſidered farther in the Third Place.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That tho' this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> of St. <hi>James</hi> had been never writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; nay, tho' there had not been one plain Text in the whole Bible expreſly aſſerting the Inſufficiency of a <hi>meer Belief,</hi> or of an empty fruitleſs <hi>Faith;</hi> yet we could not underſtand thoſe Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> wherein he ſo much magnifies <hi>Faith,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries <hi>Works,</hi> in any other Senſe than what St. <hi>James</hi> here plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teaches, without making thoſe Paſſages in St. <hi>Paul</hi> to evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate all the reſt of the Bible, and to contradict the whole De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>For there is never a Page, hardly a Verſe in the whole Bible, wherein the Nature of that Covenant which God hath made with Mankind is ſpoken of, which doth not either in expreſs Words, or by plain Conſequence contradict and diſapprove that wild Notion of being ſaved only by a bare Belief, tho we take no care to lead our Lives ſuitable to our Belief.</p>
            <p>Now this is the Method that we obſerve in the Reading of other Books; we conſider the Scope and Deſign of the whole, and judge of the Senſe of particular Paſſages with Reference to that: And if there be any ſingle Paſſage which we apprehend not the meaning of, or which, at the firſt Reading, ſeems to have another Meaning than is agreeable to the Author's main Deſign, we build nothing upon ſuch a Paſſage, but wait a while to ſee if the Author will not elſewhere explain himſelf: And if
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177314:4"/>
he does not, and if at laſt we can't diſcern how that Paſſage can, without ſomewhat ſtraining the Words, be reconcil'd with others; we conclude however, and take for granted, that the Author (if he appears to be a Perſon of Judgment) is conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with himſelf, and conſequently that in that Paſſage, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Words of it may ſound, he did not mean to thwart and cuntradict all the reſt of his Book.</p>
            <p>And this is the Caſe here; for the Deſign of our Saviour's coming into the World was to make Men Holy; all that he did, and taught, and ſuffer'd, had a tendency to effect this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and his whole Goſpel is in a manner made up of Precepts, and Exhortations, and Encouragements to Godlineſs and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and of ſevere Tnreatnings againſt all manner of Sin. [<hi>Rom.</hi> i. 18. <hi>The Wrath of God is therein reveal'd from Heaven, againſt all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs of Men, who hold the Truth in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs:</hi> theſe things are plain and undeniable; this is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly the Scope and Deſign of the whole Bible. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore altho' ſome few Paſſages in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Writings ſhou'd in their moſt obvious meaning, ſeem to imply the contrary to this; it wou'd be reaſonable however, to believe and aſſert the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſible Neceſſity of an Holy Life, together with an Othor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Belief, rather than upon them alone to ground the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which, if true, wou'd plainly evacuate all the reſt of the Bible, and perfectly thwart and contradict the whole De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>And this I think a ſure Ground for them to go upon who have not leiſure to ſtudy the point, or who after all their ſtudy, are not able clearly to diſcern how theſe two <hi>Apoſtles</hi> may be fairly reconciled in their ſeemingly contradictory Aſſertions; one ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That <hi>we are juſtify'd by Faith,</hi> and the other, That <hi>we are juſtify'd by Works, and not by Faith only,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Difference nevertheleſs I believe it is not ſo hard a Matter to reconcile, as at the firſt ſight it may appear to be; the ſeeming Contrariety between them lying, as I ſuppoſe, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their uſing in different Senſes, the Words <hi>Juſtify, Faith,</hi> and <hi>Works:</hi> Every one of which Words is capable of, and is very often in Scripture us'd in different Senſes. For,</p>
            <p n="1">I. As to the Word <hi>Juſtify,</hi> not to trouble you with the Etymology of it, which is but an uncertain way of knowing the common Acceptation of a Word; nor yet with the Senſe which Heathen Writers have us'd the Word in, from whence we cannot with certainty collect in what Senſe the Sacred Writers do uſe it; it may be ſufficient to obſerve, That the moſt obvious and uſual Signification thereof in Holy Scripture, is, to receive to Mercy, to abſolve and acquit from former Tranſgreſſions. When God juſtifies a Man, it is by forgiving him his Treſpaſſes, and accepting, eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177314:4"/>
and rewarding him as a Righteous Perſon, altho' he is not really and ſtrictly ſuch. And thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf ſeems to expound the Word, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. <hi>Being</hi> juſtify'd <hi>freely by his</hi> Grace, <hi>through the Redemption that is in Chriſt Jeſus, whom God hath ſet forth to be a propitiation thro' Faith in his Blood, to declare his Righteouſneſs for the</hi> Remiſſion <hi>of</hi> Sins <hi>that are paſt, through the forbearance of God.</hi> In which Text, <hi>being ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify'd,</hi> and <hi>having our Sins remitted,</hi> ſeem'd to be us'd as Terms of he ſame Signification. And the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> meaning to deſcribe the Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a juſtify'd Perſon, thus expreſſes it; <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are forgiven, and whoſe Sins are cover'd,</hi> (Pſal. xxxii. 1, 2.) <hi>Bleſſed is the Man to whom the Lord will not impute Sin.</hi> Rom iv. 5, 6, 7, 8.) And indeed this is all the Juſtification that Sinful Men (and ſuch all Men are) are capable of: For being in truth Sinners, they can't by a Juſt God, be acquitted as Innocent: They can therefore be juſtify'd no other way, but by having their Sins forgiven them, and by being receiv'd to Mercy; for if God ſhould <hi>enter into ſtrict Judgment with us, no Man living cou'd be juſtify'd in his Sight,</hi> as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſays, (<hi>Pſal.</hi> cxliii 2.)</p>
            <p>To juſtify therefore, in the common Scriptural Notion of it is, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve from Guilt, to diſcharge from Puniſhment; and accordingly it is frequently in Scripture oppos'd to Condemnation. <hi>It is God that juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>who is he that Condemneth? (Rom.</hi> viii. 33, 34.) And in another place, <hi>Being juſtify'd by his Blood, we ſhall be ſav'd from Wrath, through him.</hi> (Rom. v. 9.)</p>
            <p>Now taking the Word in this Senſe, there is a <hi>two fold Juſtification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> When we take upon us the Profeſſion of the Chriſtian Religion in Baptiſm; for then our paſt Sins are forgiven us, then we are receiv'd into a Covenant of Grace and Pardon.</p>
            <p>But this is not a full Juſtification; for our Sins are not then clearly par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd and forgiven, becauſe they may, after this be ſtill imputed to us; and ſo they will be, in caſe we afterwards do either in Profeſſion or in Works deny that Faith, which we then take upon us. Our <hi>Second</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and our compleat and final Juſtification is not till the great Day of Judgment, when God will for ever acquit from the Guilt, and free from the Puniſhment of all their paſt Sins, all thoſe who continu'd faithful to that Covenant, which they entred into with God at their Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>Suppoſing therefore at preſent that St <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>James</hi> do by <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Works</hi> both mean the ſame things: Yet if they do not both ſpeak of the ſame Juſtification; if St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he ſpeaks of <hi>Juſtification by Faith,</hi> means the <hi>Firſt Juſtification,</hi> which is diſpenſed to us in Baptiſm; and St. <hi>James,</hi> when he affirms, that <hi>we are juſtify'd by Works, and not by Faith only,</hi> means the Second and Final Juſtification at the laſt day; there is plainly no manner of Contrariety between them. For it may be true, that in order to our being admitted into the Covenant of Juſtification and Pardon nothing more may be required, but only that we firmly believe and embrace the Chriſtian Religion; (and accordingly we may obſerve, that as a previous Diſpoſition to Baptiſm nothing elſe ſeems to be requir'd, but only that we ſhould believe the Goſpel, and in Profeſſion renounce our
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177314:5"/>
former Sins, according to that of St. <hi>Philip</hi> to the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> Acts viii. 37. <hi>If thou believeſt with all thine Heart, thou mayſt be baptiz'd;</hi>) and yet it may be true too, that our being put into a juſtify'd ſtate by Baptiſm, will in the event be no advantage to us, but rather only increaſe our Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, unleſs afterwards we continue true and faithful to that Profeſſion which we then take upon us, and are careful to perform our part of that Covenant which we then enter into with God. Now, I ſay, this laſt ſeems to be what St <hi>James</hi> affirms, and the firſt all that St. <hi>Paul</hi> teaches, at leaſt in many of thoſe Places, where he ſays we are juſtify'd by Faith.</p>
            <p>For that by the Juſtification which St. <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of, when he ſays <hi>We are Justify'd by Works,</hi> and not by Faith only, he means our <hi>Final Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification</hi> at the great Day, upon which that Salvation will immediately be beſtow'd upon us, which at our Baptiſm was only promis'd and aſſur'd to us upon certain Conditions, is evident, by his uſing Juſtification and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in this Diſpute, as Terms equivalent. For thus he expreſſes the Doctrine of the Text, in the 14th Verſe, where he firſt begins to handle the Subject; <hi>What doth it profit, my Brethren, if a Man ſay he hath Faith and have not Works? can Faith ſave him?</hi> It is plain, that he means the ſame thing there by being ſav'd, that does in the Text and other Verſes of this Chapter, by being juſtify'd; and conſequently that by Juſtification, in this Diſcourſe of his concerning Faith and Works; he means that Final Juſtification, upon which Salvation is immediately conſequent.</p>
            <p>And on the other ſide, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> in very many at leaſt, if not in all thoſe Places wherein he attributes Juſtification to Faith only without Works, means therefore only our firſt Juſtification, that is, our being admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Covenant of Grace, and being put into a juſtify'd ſtate by Baptiſm, will, I ſuppoſe, be no leſs evident, if theſe two things be conſider'd.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That in many places he ſpeaks of Juſtification as a thing paſt, which he cou'd not do if he had meant the ſame thing by Juſtification that St. <hi>James</hi> does. For thus writing to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> he ſays, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> vi 11, <hi>Ye are,</hi> or ye have been <hi>juſtify'd in the Name of the Lord Jeſus:</hi> And <hi>Rom.</hi> vi. 1. ſpeaking of himſelf and other Chriſtians that were then living, and conſequently not <hi>finally juſtify'd</hi> in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Uſe of the Word, he ſays, that <hi>being juſtify'd by Faith they had Peace with God.</hi> And upon this he grounds their Hope that they ſhould alſo, if they continu'd in Faith, be <hi>finally juſtify'd</hi> by God at the laſt Day, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>For if while we were Sinners Chriſt dy'd for us, much more then, being now juſtify'd by his Blood, we ſhall be ſav'd from Wrath thro' him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It may be alſo further obſerv'd, That in many places he expreſly joyns Juſtification with Baptiſm, as an Effect or Concomitant of it; as in <hi>Tit.</hi> iii. 5, 7. <hi>Not by Works of Righteouſneſs which we have done, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Mercy he ſav'd us by the waſhing of Regeneration, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of the Holy Ghoſt,—that being justify'd by his Grace, we ſhou'd be made Heirs according to the Hope of Eternal Life;</hi> and in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> vi. 11. <hi>Such were ſome of you; but ye are waſh'd, but ye are ſanctify'd, but ye are juſtify'd, they were juſtify'd,</hi> it ſeems, at the ſame time that they were waſh'd, that is, at their Baptiſm, when they openly and ſolemnly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:177314:5"/>
thoſe wicked Works which they had formerly liv'd in, and took up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them the Profeſſion of the Chriſtian Faith.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, if this be granted, which ſeems to be very probable. That St. <hi>Paul</hi> generally means this by <hi>Juſtification, (viz.</hi> only our being admitted into a State of Grace and Favour with God, at our Baptiſm, in which State if we continue by perſevering in Faith and Obedience, we ſhall at laſt be juſtify'd and acquitted finally in the great Judgment;) it will be eaſy to underſtand all thoſe Places wherein he attributes this to Faith only, in a Senſe very agreeable to the Doctrine which St. <hi>James</hi> here teaches; it will be eaſy then to underſtand what St. <hi>Paul</hi> means, <hi>Rom.</hi> iv. 5. where he ſays, That God <hi>juſtifies the Ungodly;</hi> then, I ſay, that Paſſage which hath been thought the ſtrongeſt, will appear to be no Objection at all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt St. <hi>James</hi>'s Doctrine; the meaning thereof being only this, That the Grace of God in Chriſt Jeſus is ſo large, as that he do's not refuſe even the vileſt and greateſt Sinners, but readily accepts them to Favour, upon their Belief of the Goſpel, and cloſing with the Terms of it: And there will be then no difficulty at all in underſtanding how <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>juſtify'd by Faith only,</hi> according to St <hi>Paul,</hi> and how he was <hi>juſtify'd by Works,</hi> that is, not by <hi>Faith</hi> only, as St. <hi>James</hi> expreſly affirms he was, at the 21ſt Verſe of this Chapter. For the Caſe was thus: Upon his giving a full and hearty Aſſent to the Truth of the Divine Promiſes, he was immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiv'd into God's Favour and Acceptance, even before the Sincerity of his Faith has been actually try'd by his Obedience: <hi>Abraham believed God, and it was counted to him for Righteouſneſs,</hi> Rom. iv. 3. ſo that he was then in a juſtify'd ſtate: And yet, if after this he had declin'd to leave his Country and his Father's Houſe, or even to ſacrifice his Son at God's Command, he wou'd by this Diſobedience have fall'n from that ſtate of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Favour, and not have been finally juſtify'd by God; but then all his former (as well as his later ſins, which had been once remitted to him, with a temporary and conditional Remiſſion, upon his firſt entring into the Covenant of Grace, by <hi>Faith,</hi> (by virtue of which Remiſſion, he was, while he continu'd in the Covenant, a juſtify'd Perſon) wou'd nevertheleſs have been imputed to him, and he condemn'd for them, if he had afterwards ſwerv'd from his Obedience.</p>
            <p>In ſhort therefore, the Juſtification which St. <hi>Paul</hi> generally ſpeaks of, is that whereby we are made Heirs of Salvation, as he himſelf explains it, in the afore-cited Text <hi>Tit.</hi> iii. 7. <hi>That being juſtify'd by Grace we ſhou'd be made Heirs, according to the Hope of eternal Life:</hi> but the Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which St. <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of, is that by which we are actually admitted into the Poſſeſſion of this Inheritance. And therefore, tho' in order to the firſt Juſtification nothing more be neceſſary but only that we cloſe with, and accept of thoſe Terms of Reconciliation, which God offers to us: Yet in order to the Second Juſtification, it is moreover neceſſary, that we ſhou'd make good that Covenant which we before entred into; or elſe, tho' we are already juſtify'd in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Senſe, that is, are now already by our embracing and believing and profeſſing the Goſpel, in ſuch a Capacity and Likelihood of obtaining eternal Life, as an <hi>Heir</hi> is of enjoying his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Eſtate; we ſhal' never be juſtify'd in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Senſe, that is, we
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177314:6"/>
ſhall never actually poſſeſs and enjoy the Eſtate; but notwithſtanding our preſent Heirſhip, ſhall at laſt be caſt off, and diſinherited for our Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. And this Obſervation concerning the different Senſes, wherein theſe two Apoſtles do ſometimes uſe the Word juſtify, may, I ſuppoſe, be alone ſufficient to reconcile them in moſt, if not in all thoſe aſſages wherein they ſeem to differ. But, II. The Word Faith or Belief, which they do both uſe in treating of this Subject, is likewiſe a Word capable of, and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in Scripture us'd in different Senſes; and I believe it may eaſily be made appear, that in thoſe Places wherein St. <hi>Paul</hi> attributes ſo much to Faith, wherein he is thought to declare that that is the only Condition of our final Juſtification, and admittance into the Promis'd Inheritance, he means quite another thing by Faith than St. <hi>James</hi> does, when he ſays that that alone is not ſufficient, even all that St. <hi>James</hi> means by Faith and Works too. I will not trouble you now with all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gnifications, in which the Word Faith or Belief is us'd in Holy Scripture; but ſhall take no ice only of two, which I ſuppoſe moſt applicable to the caſe in hand.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Firſt Senſe of it which I ſhall take notice of, is that which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is the moſt obvious and proper meaning of the Word; that is, when by Faith is meant, <hi>An aſſent of the Mind to the Truth of ſome Reveal'd Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> And in this Senſe St. <hi>James</hi> uſes the Word: By that Faith, which being without Works, he ſays, is not ſufficient to juſtifie or ſave us, he plainly means nothing more than only a Belief of thoſe Truths, which are reveal'd in the Goſpel. And the Caſe that he puts, is this, That a Man believes there is a God, and that thoſe things which he has reveal'd are true, and that all his Promiſes and Threatnings ſhall be made good, but never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs takes no care to live well; and in this caſe he ſays, that ſuch a Faith as this is an empty dead Faith, and that it will be of no real advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to us, any more than it is to the Devil's, who believe all theſe Truths as firmly as we can do, but without any Benefit to themſelves, becauſe the Promiſes being not made to them, they are not thereby incited to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of good. But the Promiſes are made to us, and therefore it can hardly be conceived, it is ſcarcely to be ſuppoſed that any Man that firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believes all the Truths of the Goſpel, and conſiders his own Intereſt therein, ſhould nevertheleſs allow himſelf in a wicked Life. Faith is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally ſuch an active, lively, and working Principle, that it can hardly fail to ſhew it ſelf by its Effects:</p>
            <p n="2">2. And for this Reaſon, Secondly, the word Faith, which moſt proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſignifies nothing but the Cauſe or Principle, is oftentimes in Scripture put to ſignifie both the Cauſe and the Effect too, that is, both a Belief of the Goſpel-Truths, and alſo a Life led anſwerably to ſuch a Belief.</p>
            <p>And in this large and comprehenſive ſenſe 'tis clearly evident St. <hi>Paul</hi> does uſe the word in divers places, and eſpecially in thoſe Epiſtles where he treats of Juſtification by Faith, as may appear from his oftentimes uſing othe Words and Phraſes inſtead of the ſingle word Faith. For whhat he ſometimes calls Faith, he at other times in thoſe ſame Epiſtles, calls <hi>the Law of Faith, and the Obedience of Faith, (Rom.</hi> iii. 27. i. 5. xvi. 26. And in <hi>Rom.</hi> x. 16. he moſt clearly explains his own meaning to be, to include and comprehend Obedience in the word Faith, whenever he attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177314:6"/>
ſo much to Faith: <hi>But they have not all obeyed the Goſpel, for</hi> Eſaias <hi>ſaith, Lord, who hath believ'd our Report?</hi> In which words the ſame thing is plainly meant by <hi>obeying the Goſpel,</hi> and believing the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Preachers of it; from whence it clearly appears, That the Faith or Belief which he ſo much magnifies in that Epiſtle, is not an idle, ineffectual Belief, but ſuch a Faith as makes Men to be obedient.</p>
            <p>Foraſmuch therefore as the Faith which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, when he ſays we are juſtify'd by Faith, includes in it all that St. <hi>James</hi> means by Faith and Works too; it is plain, That tho' we ſuppoſe that they do both uſe the word juſtifie always in the ſame ſenſe, there is not, however, any Contrariety in their Doctrines, altho' one ſays that <hi>we are juſtify d by Faith,</hi> and the other that <hi>we are juſtify'd by Works and not by ſaith only.</hi> But 3. There is alſo an ambiguity in the word <hi>Works:</hi> and it is not improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, (nay, I ſuppoſe I ſhall make it very plain) that theſe two <hi>Apoſtles</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> and S. <hi>Jam.</hi> in their ſeveral Diſcourſes upon the Subject of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> do likewiſe uſe this Word in very different Senſes; and that St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he excludes <hi>Works,</hi> do's not mean the ſame by Works that St. <hi>James</hi> do's, when he affirms that we are juſtify'd by Works, and not by Faith only. And if St. <hi>James</hi> by Works, when he affirms them to be neceſſary together with Faith, means thoſe Works of Piety, Juſtice and Charity, and other Moral Duties which are required in the Goſpel; as to any one that reads the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of the Chapter it will be evident that he do's; and on the other ſide, if St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he excludes Works, means by Works only, either thoſe materially good Works, which Men might do without the Grace of the Goſpel, or the Merit of good VVorks, or elſe thoſe Ritual Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances which were requir'd by the Ceremonial Law of <hi>Moſes:</hi> then, tho' their VVords and Expreſſions be different, yet their Senſe may be the very ſame. Now concerning this place in St. <hi>James,</hi> I think there can be no Diſpute; he plainly takes both Faith and VVorks in the moſt proper and uſual acceptation of the words: By Faith, when he affirms that Faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone is not ſufficient, he plainly means a meer Belief of the Truths of the Goſpel; and by VVorks, when he affirms that they are neceſſary together with Faith, he plainly means ſuch a ſort of Life and Converſation, as the Belief of the Goſpel Truths is naturally apt to produce, <hi>a Converſation becoming the Goſpel of Chriſt:</hi> And both theſe he affirms to be neceſſary, in order to our final Juſtification at the laſt day. And on the other ſide, St <hi>Paul,</hi> if at any time he ſpeaks of the ſame Juſtification that St. <hi>James</hi> do's, means, by Faith, when he ſays we are juſtify'd by that only, all that St. <hi>James</hi> means by Faith and VVorks too (as hath been ſhewn already) and by Works, when he ſays we are juſtify'd by Works, he means only, either the Merit of good VVorks, or ſuch VVorks as might be done by unregenerate Men without the Grace of the Goſpel, or elſe the Ritual Obſervances of the Moſaical Law. And that he uſes the VVords in theſe Senſes, and do's not mean to exclude from being a condition of our final Juſtification that hearry Obedience to the Precepts of the Goſpel, which a firm Belief of the Truths of it is naturally apt to produce, will further appear if theſe two things be conſidered: 1 The occaſion and deſign of thoſe Diſcourſes of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> wherein Faith is ſo much magnified, and VVorks are ſet ſo light by: And
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177314:7"/>
And, 2 The ſeveral Cautions that are here and there intermix'd in thoſe Diſcourſes, as it were on purpoſe to prevent our miſtaking his meaning, and thinking that we may be ſav'd by Faith alone, without a good Life.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We may conſider the Occaſion and Deſign of thoſe Diſcourſes, of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> wherein Faith is ſo much magnify'd, and Works are ſet ſo light by; and which conſequently do ſeem moſt to contradict the Doctrine here taught by St. <hi>James.</hi> And I premiſe this firſt of all; That none of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles ſeem to have been written as if they were intended to comprehend the whole Chriſtian Religion; they rather ſuppoſe Chriſtianity already planted in thoſe Places, to which his Epiſtles are directed. It was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently his Intention, in every Epiſtle that he wrote, to teach all the <hi>Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and to lay again the foundation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance from dead Works, and of Faith towards God;</hi> Heb. vi. 1. for all this had been done before; thoſe ſame Apoſtles, by whoſe Miniſtry they had been converted and baptiz'd, having alſo then, (according to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion given them by Chriſt) <hi>taught them to obſerve all things whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our Lord had commanded.</hi> As ſuch therefore the Apoſtle conſider'd the Perſons to whom he wrote, <hi>viz.</hi> as true Diſciples of Chriſt, as Perſons that had before been taught to obey as believe the Goſpel; and ſo had no fear upon him, that by his uſing the Word Faith or Works in an uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Senſe (and yet in ſuch a Senſe as the Controverſy he was handling led him to uſe them in) they to whom he wrote, wou'd ever be in danger of embracing an Opinion ſo contrary to the firſt Principles of the Chriſtian Religion, as it plainly was, to think that they might be ſaved only by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, without obeying the Goſpel. The main deſign then I ſay, of moſt of St <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, I mean of the Controverſial Parts of them, ſeems to be to furniſh the Chriſtians to whom he wrote, with Anſwers to thoſe Objections, which the Enemies to Chriſtianity, among whom they liv'd, did make againſt it. And moſt of the Churches to which theſe Epiſtles were directed, were made up chiefly of <hi>Gentile Converts,</hi> with whom neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, there were ſome <hi>Jewiſh Converts</hi> alſo intermix'd; but the far greateſt part of the Inhabitants of thoſe places were profeſs'd <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who, tho' both zealous, each for their own way, and againſt each other, yet readily joyn'd their Forces together as againſt a common Enemy, to hinder the growth and ſpreading of Chriſtianity. So that St. <hi>Paul</hi> had three ſorts of Adverſaries to deal with, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the <hi>Judaizing Christians.</hi> The <hi>Gentiles;</hi> who had been long bred up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Inſtitution of their Philoſophers, and by their good and wholſom Precepts of Morality, were in a good readineſs and diſpoſition to embrace the Goſpel; which, in general, commanded little more than they were taught before their own Philoſophers, only requiring a ſtricter and more perfect obſervance of thoſe Rules, and adding new Motives and Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to it, from the plain Revelation of a future ſtate of Rewards and Puniſhments, of which, before the coming of Chriſt, Men had but an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure Notion, and very ſlender Aſſurance. The main Objection therefore which theſe had to make againſt St. <hi>Paul,</hi> was, that he took (as they thought) a great deal of pains to little purpoſe, in going about to eſtabliſh a new Belief, and a new Profeſſion of Religion among them, ſeeing that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177314:7"/>
al to Practice they had been taught all the ſame things in ſubſtance by their own Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers; ſo that conſequently they thought, he might have ſpared his labour. They were of the mind of our Modern Deiſts, That Natural Religion was ſo good and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, that it needed no Revelation to improve it. Againſt theſe therefore the Apoſtle proves the neceſſity of the Chriſtian Diſpenſation, and of Faith in Chriſt: Becauſe tho' Men had been taught well before, they had never practiced as they had been taught; that by reaſon of the weakneſs of humane Nat re, they had never liv'd up to what they knew was their Duty; that therefore no Man was or cou'd be juſtified in God's ſight, by the Law of Nature, or the firſt Covenant made with Mankind, which requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſtrict and unſinning Obedience; that conſequently it was neceſſary to believe in Chriſt, and to enter into that more gracious Covenant, which he by his Blood had made, between God and us, whereby he had encouraged good Works with better Promiſes, and offered to afford us divine ſtrength and ſuccour to aſſiſt our Endeavours; by which Covenant of Grace in Chriſt (tho' indeed we were ſtill obliged to the ſame Duties which the Law of Natute had laid upon us) we might be juſtified, which by the other we could not be; becauſe that required ſtrict and unſinning Obedience, whereas this made allowance for the weakneſs of Humane Nature, and left room for Repentance, if at any time through careleſsneſs or ſurprize we ſhould come ſhort of our Duty. And to ſhew the advantage of this Covenant made by Chriſt, and the impoſſibility of being juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any other way, than by having our Sins remitted to us through Faith in his Blood, ſeems to have been mainly deſigned by the Apoſtle in the former part of his Epiſtle to the Romans. Now the firſt Covenant made with Mankind being indeed a Covenant of Works, without Grace, therefore in oppoſition to, and to diſtinguiſh this from that, he with good Reaſon, calls this, ſometimes Grace, ſometimes the Law of Faith, ſometimes the preaching of Faith, and ſometimes barely Faith; which he ſays is the only way by which it is poſſible for us to be juſtified, becauſe our Nature is ſo corrupt and dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera e, that we cannot perform perfect and unſinning Obedience. But, 2. The Jews were alſo as conceited of themſelves as the Gentiles, and as unwilling to accept of the Covenant made by Chriſt, becauſe they truſted to be ſaved by the Obſervation of the Law of Moſes. And therefore the Apoſtle likewiſe, againſt theſe, endeavours to ſhew that they were Sinners as well as the Gentiles, and ſtood in as much need of a Saviour as they. And this he does in the four or five 1ſt Chapters of his Epiſtl to the Romans; in ſome Paſſages of which (eſpecially in the firſt and ſecond Chapters) he ſeems to have a peculiar Reſpect to the Gentiles; and in other places to the Jews more eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and in ſome to both of them. And the ſum of this Argument is this; That ſince all, both Jews and Gentiles had ſinned, and come ſhort of the Glory of God, it was therefore neceſſary that a Redeemer ſhould come, to make attonement for their paſt Sins, and to eſtabliſh a new Covenant between God and Men; which he calls Faith, or the Law or Faith, to diſtinguiſh it from the Law of Moſes, which was truly a Law of Works; and by this Covenant of Grace or Faith in Chriſt, which was open and free for all to enter into, both Jews and Gentiles, he ſays, might be juify'd, which they could not either of them be by the Law of Works, nor the Jews any more than the Gentiles by the Ceremonial Law of Moſes; that being never deſign'd by God as a C ndition of Juſtifica ion, as having only temporal Rewards and Puniſhments annexed to it. Seeing therefore the Jews as well as the Gentiles had broken the firſt Law gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Mankind, which requir'd unſinning Obedience, he ſays there was no means of Juſtifi ation now left for either of them, but by Faith in Chriſt, that is, by coming into that New Covenant which Chriſt had eſtabliſhed by his Death, and offered to us in the Goſpel. But, 3. Beſides theſe two, the Apoſtle had alſo a third ſort of Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries to deal with, which did coſt him as much trouble as either of the former; and they were ſome who being born and bred Jews, had been converted by Chriſtianity by the Preaching of the apoſtles, but nevertheleſs ſtill retained ſuch a great Likeing and Veneration for Moſes and his Law, that they thought they were yet bound to obſerve it as much as ever; and not only ſo, but they would fain have forced the ſame upon the Gentiles too, telling them that notwithſtanding Chriſt, they were bound to be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed as the Jews w re, and to keep the Law of Moſes, and that otherwiſe they could not be ſaved. Againſt theſe therefore, the Apoſtle proves at large, eſpecially in his Epiſtle to the Galatians) that the Law given by Moſes was never deſigned to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177314:8"/>
oblige the Gentiles, nor the Jews neither any longer than till the coming of Chriſt; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that Law was, to the Jews themſelves, only School-maſter to bring them unto Chriſt, that is, to prepare and diſpoſe them to receive his more pure and heavenly Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; that therefore now, after the Revelation and preaching of the Goſpel, that Law was of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> uſe: And after that Faith is come, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is after the Goſpel is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, we are no longer under a School-maſter, Galat. iii. 25. That the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony in Law was made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> only of Types and Shadows, whereof Chriſt was the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Subſtance being now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that the Ceremonial Law was given only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> exerciſe the Jewiſh Nation for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and was then to give way to a better Law the Law of Faith or Evangelical Obedience; that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> himſelf was juſtified by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> means and method which is now propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed inn Goſpel, by viz. by a lively Faith in the Promiſes of God working in him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Obedience whatſoever God required of him; and that he was thus juſtified before he was circumciſed, and therefore ſo might they be too, without Circumciſion, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Obſervances.</p>
            <p>In the management of which diſpute with theſe Judaizing Chriſtians, the Apoſtle calls the Chriſtian Religion, as oppos'd to the Jewiſh, by the word Faith to diſtinguiſh it from the Obſervation of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law, which was call d Works, or the Works of the Law. And uſing the word in this ſenſe, he ſays, We are juſtify'd by Faith, and by Faith only, that is, by the Faith and Obedience of the Goſpel; and that there is no need at all of Works, that is, of ſuch Works as were enjoyn'd by the Ceremonial Law, which they laid ſuch great ſtreſs upon; for thus he often explains himſelf, expreſly calling thoſe Works which he rejects, the Works of the Law, thereby plainly diſtinguiſhing them from the Works of Evangelical Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and clearly imitating that it was not his intention to exclude theſe, tho' he did thoſe. Thus the Apoſtle manag'd the Controverſy he was engag'd in with theſe three Adverſaries: And that h s main Deſign was to oppoſe one or other of them in all thoſe Places wherein thoſe Paſſages are found which ſo much magnifie Faith, and vilifie Works (which are eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Epiſtles to the Romans and Galatians) will, I ſuppoſe, readily appear to any one that ſhall attentively read them over; and I think it will be impoſſible to make out the Context, or to ſhew how thoſe places do at all tend to the carrying on theſe Deſigns, if we take the words Faith and Works in any other Senſe than I have before ſaid St. <hi>Paul</hi> does uſe them in. But, Secondly, That the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> did not intend to exclude ſuch good Works as St. <hi>James</hi> here requires (<hi>viz.</hi> Obedience to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of the Goſpel) from being neceſſary to our final Juſtification at the great day, will yet further and more plainly appear, if in reading over thoſe Epiſtles, we do but obſerve the ſeveral Cautions that are here and there intermix'd as it were on purpoſe to prevent our putting ſuch an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation upon his Words. And firſt in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> in Chap. ii. Ver. 6. he tells us plainly, that <hi>God will render to every Man according to his Works, Tribulation and Anguiſh upon every Soul of Man that doth evil; and Glory, Honour and Peace, to every Man that worketh good:</hi> Which Paſſage would be very odly put in, in a Diſcourſe wherein he was proving the ſufficiency of Faith alone for Juſtification, if thereby he had meant ſuch a Faith as might be without good Works.</p>
            <p>But in the 13th Verſe of that Chapter he contradicts that Opinion moſt expreſly: <hi>Not the Hearers of the Law,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſhall be juſt before God, but the</hi> Doers <hi>of the aw ſhall be juſtify'd.</hi> It ſeems then that St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Juſtification by <hi>Faith</hi> only, was not a <hi>Juſtification</hi> without
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177314:8"/>
Works; the Faith that he there ſpeaks of, muſt needs therefore be ſuch a Faith as includes Works in it; <hi>The Doers of the Law ſhall be juſtified.</hi> And ſo again, <hi>Chap.</hi> iii. <hi>V.</hi> 21. after he had ſaid that both Circumciſion and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſion muſt be juſtify'd by Faith; and that they could not be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd any other way; that they might not take Faith in ſuch a narrow ſenſe as to exclude good Works, he adds, <hi>Do we then make void the Law through Faith? God forbid; Yea, we eſtabliſh the Law.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe again, <hi>Chap. vi Ver.</hi> 1. <hi>What ſhall we ſay then? ſhall we conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in Sin that Grace may abound? God forbid How ſhall we that are dead to Sin live any longer therein?</hi> And again, <hi>Ver.</hi> 15. <hi>What then? ſhall we ſin, becauſe we are not under the Law, but under Grace? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid.</hi> And laſtly, (to name no more) in the viiith Chapter of that Epiſtle, Ver. 1. when he was come to the Concluſion of this Controverſy, having ſhewn at large the inſufficiency of all other ways, and the abſolute neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of accepting the Goſpel Truths, in order to Juſtification, he goes on to ſhew the Bleſſedneſs of thoſe who believ'd in Chriſt, in theſe words; <hi>There is therefore now no Condemnation to them which are in Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> But then, leſt they ſhould miſtake him, and think that a bare Belief in Chriſt, or the profeſſion of his Religion only, was enough to entitle them to this Bleſſedneſs, he adds, <hi>who walk not after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit,</hi> The like Care he has alſo taken in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians</hi> where he handles this Controverſy again, with a ſpecial reſpect to the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Law; where we may obſerve, that to prevent all Miſunderſtanding of what he had delivered touching the ſufficiency of Faith without Works, he takes frequent occaſion to declare his meaning to be, only to exclude the Works of the Law, not the obedience of the Goſpel. Particularly in the two laſt Chapters he is very large in explaining what kind of Liberty he had been before pleading for; <hi>Stand faſt therefore,</hi> ſays he, <hi>in the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty wherewith Chriſt has made us free, and be not entangled again with the Yoke of Bondage.</hi> Galat. v. 1. And what Bondage he meant, appears in the next Verſe. <hi>Behold, I</hi> Paul <hi>ſay unto you, that if you be circumciſed, Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing;</hi> that is, if you ſtill truſt to be ſav'd by your Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Obſervances, you diſclaim and renounce the Covenant which Chriſt hath made for you, and ſo can expect no benefit from it; <hi>Whoſoever of you,</hi> ſays he, <hi>are juſtify'd,</hi> that is, hope to be juſtify'd, <hi>by the Law ye are fallen from Grace. For we, through the Spirit, wait for the hope of Rightoouſneſs by Faith; We,</hi> that is, <hi>We Chriſtians,</hi> no leſs than you <hi>Jews, do wait for the Hope of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> that is, for a Reward of our Righteouſneſs: But then it is not ſuch a Righteouſneſs as yours, a Righteouſneſs conſiſting in the obſervation of Rites and Ceremonies, but thro' the Spirit, that is, by a Spiritual Righteouſneſs; and 'tis by Faith, that is, 'tis ſuch a Righteouſneſs as is wrought in us by Faith, that is, by our Belief of the Goſpel of Chriſt. For ſays he, Ver. 6. <hi>in Christ Jeſus neither Circumciſion availeth any thing, nor Uncircumciſion, but Faith; not any Faith, but Faith which worketh by Love,</hi> or Faith which is made perfect by Love, Which words he repeats again in Chap. vi. <hi>V.</hi> 15. only inſtead of Faith putting in another Word, not ſo ambiguous; <hi>In Chriſt Jeſus, neither Circumciſion availeth any thing, nor Uncircumciſion but a new Creatuse.</hi> And the ſame Apoſtle in another parallel place, in another of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177314:9"/>
his Epiſtles, puts it out of all doubt what he means in the firſt of theſe places, by <hi>Faith,</hi> when he expreſſes the ſame by Obedience; <hi>Circumciſion is nothing, and Uncircumciſion but the keeping the Commandments of God,</hi> 1 Cor. vii. 19. And now by all that hath been ſaid, I ſuppoſe, it ſufficiently <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that by <hi>Faith,</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> means ſomething more than only a bare belief <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Goſpel Truths, when he makes it the ſole Condition of Juſtification; and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Works, he does not mean Works of Evangelical Obedience, when he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes them from being neceſſary in order to it: So that <hi>Paul</hi> does not, any more than St. <hi>James</hi> exclude ſuch good Works as are the natural Effects of true, lively, and Chriſtian <hi>Faith,</hi> from being neceſſary together with <hi>Faith,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der to our full and final Juſtification at the laſt day. And from all that hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> been ſaid, I think it appears, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>James</hi> agree very well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; which was the point that I propos'd to make good, St. <hi>James</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſays here, that Faith alone, or a bare Belief of the Goſpel, will not do without Works anſwerable to our Belief; <hi>Ye ſee how that by Works a Man is juſtify'd and not by Faith only:</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> on the other ſide ſays, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are juſtify'd by Faith: but tho' this manner of Expreſſion be different from and in the Letter, ſeemingly contradictory to St. <hi>James</hi>'s meaning is plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly the ſame. He affirms, indeed, that we are juſtified by Faith: but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as I have ſhewn, he means the ſame thing by <hi>Faith,</hi> that St. <hi>James</hi> does by <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Works</hi> too; he mans ſuch a Faith as a <hi>Abraham</hi>'s was, (for that is his Example as well as St. <hi>James</hi>'s;) he means ſuch a Faith as however it is try'd, approves it ſelf by a ready Obedience, as <hi>Abraham</hi>'s did: and the Works which he rejects as uſeleſs and unneceſſary, or as not ſufficient are not ſuch as <hi>Abraham</hi>'s were, the Fruits of a lively Faith; but either meer ritual Obſervances, or elſe ſuch Works, as though materially good are not done out of a good and virtuous Principle. In a word, he oppoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Faith, his juſtifying and ſaving Faith, not to Evangelical Obedience; but either to unſinning Obedience, by which none can be juſtify'd, becauſe all are Sinners; or to an Opinion of Merit, which there can never be any Ground for; or, laſtly, to the Rites and Ceremonies of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law, which Law, he ſhews, was not then obliging, and ſo cou'd not be the Condition of Juſtification.</p>
            <p>The uſe we ſhall make of what hath been ſaid upon this Subject, is this; we ſhould be hereby incited to the diligent performance of that whole Condition that (according to the Doctrine taught by both theſe Apoſtles (is requir'd of us in order to Salvation; which is not only to believe in Chriſt, and to make prefeſſion of the Chriſtian Faith, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to live as becomes the Goſpel of Chriſt, and to bring forth plenteouſly all the fruitful of Righteouſneſs. And this likewiſe St. Peter teaches in his 2d Epiſtle, i. 5. &amp;c. with whoſe Words I ſhall conclude; Beſides this, giving all diligence add to your Faith Vir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue, and to vir ue knowledge; and to knowledge temperance, and to temperance patience and to patience, godlineſs; and to godlineſs, Brotherly kindneſs; and to bro herly kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Charity. For if theſe things be in you and abound, they make you that you ſhall nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be barren nor unfruitful in the knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, But he that lacketh theſe things, is blind, and cannot ſee afar off, and hath forgotten that he was purged from his old Sins. Wherefore the rather, Brethren, give diligence to make your Calling and Election ſure: for if ye do theſe things ye ſhall never fall: For ſo an entrance ſhall be miniſtred unto you abundantly, into the everlaſting Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Which God of his infinite Mercy grant, for the ſake of the ſame our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; To whom,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
